Today's דף daf *daf* is קכט *Kuf Chaf Tet*, 129, the last
דף *daf* of this פרק perek *perek*, which has been certainly challenging
in terms of dealing with dangling limbs and skin and meat and
all these laws of טומאה tumah, *tumah* and טהרה *taharah*. Yes, 129,
and we actually will end today with another משנה Mishna *mishna* about
humans. Anyway, we pick
up at the bottom of קכח *Kuf Chaf Chet* עמוד ב' *Amud
Bet*, where it's תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabanan*, four lines from the bottom,
right near the little א' *Aleph* in brackets, in half brackets. תנו
רבנן *Tanu Rabanan*. So again we are dealing with issues about dangling
limbs and the status of אבר מן החי eiver min hachai. *ever
min hachai* when the animal dies, the limb is like it fell
off, became an אבר מן החי eiver min hachai, *ever min hachai*,
but אבר מן החי ever min ha-chai. *ever min hachai* causes טומאה
tumah. *tumah*, בשר מן החי Basar Min HaChai. *basar min hachai*, flesh
does not. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabanan*, our rabbis taught: החותך כזית kezayit
בשר מאבר מן החי *Hachotech kezayit basar me'ever min hachai*, if you
cut a כזית *kezayit* of meat—רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it shouldn't be
כזית *kezayit* because we're talking about it as food to become טמא
tamei *tamei* and therefore the size is really more like a כביצה
*kabeitzah*, an egg, but anyway, regardless of that, you cut a piece
of meat off of an אבר מן החי ever min ha-chai. *ever
min hachai*. So the אבר מן החי ever min ha-chai *ever min
hachai*, remember, is a source of טומאה tumah *tumah*. However, the meat
from the אבר מן החי Ever Min HaChai, *ever min hachai*, that's
the full אבר ever? *ever*. The meat is not a source of
טומאה tumah *tumah*. The question here—the meat can become—if you tore off
the meat it won't be טמא tamei. *tamei*, it can receive טומאה
tumah? *tumah* as food, right? So the meat of an אבר מן
החי Ever Min HaChai *ever min hachai* is not a source of
טומאה tumah *tumah*, but it can receive טומאה tumah. *tumah* as food,
but to be considered food, you have to be חישב עליו *chishev
alav*, you have to plan on eating it, because an אבר מן
החי Ever Min HaChai *ever min hachai* is normally not eaten, not
eaten by Jews, not eaten by non-Jews, at least halachically. So therefore
you need to say "I'm planning on eating this piece of meat"
to make it food. So again, you have the whole אבר ever
*ever*, it's a source of טומאה tumah? *tumah*. You cut off a
piece of meat, it stops being an אבר Ever? *ever*, stops being
a whole limb, it no longer is a source of טומאה tumah
*tumah*. Is it susceptible for receiving טומאה tumah. *tumah*? Only if you
planned on eating it. So that's the case. You cut off a
piece of meat from this limb, חתכו ואחר כך חישב עליו *chatcho
ve'ach kach chishev alav*, if
first you cut it off and then you plan to eat it,
טהור tahor. *tahor*, then it is טהור tahor, *tahor*. I mean, until
it comes in contact with something טמא tamei, *tamei*, but at this
stage it still is טהור tahor, *tahor*, it still is pure. חישב
עליו ואחר כך חתכו *Chishev alav ve'ach kach chatcho*, you planned on
eating it when it was attached to the limb. You said, "Oh,
that looks like a yummy piece of meat," and therefore you cut
it off. So first you planned on eating it, then you cut
it off. So its definition of food preceded being cut off from
the limb. In this type of case, טמא tamei? *tamei*, it is
טמא Tamei *tamei*. Now why is that? So the basic point is
like this: because what happens? This thing that you are cutting off
is at—if it's food, it's also coming in contact when it's part
of the limb, it's in contact with something טמא Tamei *tamei*. So
so that when it's a part of the limb and it is
a source of טומאה tumah, *tumah*, and now you're removing it, should
it at least—and it stops being a source—should it at least receive
טומאה tumah. *tumah* because it was in contact, it was part of
the very source of טומאה tumah. *tumah* itself? So if you decided
as food after the fact, then the answer is of course no,
because it only can become receive טומאה tumah, *tumah* after it's separate
from the source of טומאה tumah *tumah*. So you cut a piece
of meat away and then you made it into food, then it's
no longer in contact with the original limb and it can become
טמא Tamei. *tamei* in the future, but it's not טמא Tamei. *tamei*
now. But if you designated it as food while it was part
of the limb, so in that state it was a source of
טומאה tumah. *tumah*, but it also could receive טומאה tumah *tumah* from
the limb that it was a part of, and then you removed
it, so it retains the טומאה tumah *tumah* from that it received
when it was as part of the limb. It's not a source
of טומאה tumah, *tumah*, but because it was defined as food when
it was connected to the limb, it received that טומאה tumah, *tumah*.
Okay, so that's the ruling there. רבי אסי Rabbi Assi *Rabbi Assi*,
okay, now that's the end of that ruling. רבי אסי Rabbi Assi
לא עלה בבי מדרשא *Rabbi Assi lo ala be'midrasha*. One day רבי
אסי Rabbi Assi *Rabbi Assi* didn't make it to the בית מדרש
Beis Medrash. *beis medrash*. He had some business to take care of.
Okay, now אשכחיה *ashchei*, I'm sure it was very important business that
could not be delayed. Now אשכחיה לרבי זירא *ashchei le'Rabbi Zeira*, he
found רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira. *Rabbi Zeira*. Now of course this was
a very responsible member of the בית מדרש *beis medrash*, so even
if you're not there you have to catch up the missed work.
So he said to רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira *Rabbi Zeira*, אמר ליה
amar lei, *amar lei*, מאי אמור בבי מדרשא *mai amar be'bei midrasha*?
What was said in the בית מדרש *beis medrash* yesterday? I need
to catch up, they didn't have digital recordings, so I needed to
catch up. So אמר ליה amar lei, *amar lei*, so he said
to him, מאי קשיא לך *mai kashya lach*? There must be something
that's bothering you from the סוגיא *sugya* we were learning that you
want to know how it was dealt with, right? You know, he
couldn't just be סתם *stahm* curious, but he got a sense that
the reason he was asking was because they were in the middle
of learning a סוגיא *sugya*, presumably this פרק perek *perek*, our משנה
Mishna, *mishna*, and something was bothering him, so he wanted to know
what was said about it. So what bothered you about what we've
been learning recently? So אמר ליה amar lei, *amar lei*, he said
to him, דתניא De'tanya, *de'tanya*, because this ברייתא braisa, *braisa* that we
just taught: חישב ואחר כך חתכו
טמא tamei *chishev ve'ach
kach chatcho tamei*, if first you plan to eat it and then
you cut it, it's טמא tamei. *tamei* because you made it food
and then you removed it, so it received טומאה tumah, *tumah* by
being in contact with the limb itself that it was a part
of. So he says, I don't get why it was in contact.
דף קכט עמוד א' *Daf Kuf Chaf Tet Amud Aleph*, טומאת בית
הסתרים היא *tumas beis hastarim hi*, it only touched in the—in the
hidden place. טומאת בית הסתרים לא מטמא metamei. *Tumas beis hastarim lo
metamei*, and that doesn't transfer טומאה tumah. *tumah*, meaning what? If I'm
cutting a piece of meat away from a limb, so when it's
part of the limb, it's a source of טומאה, tumah, it's not
receiving טומאה, tumah. it's a source of טומאה. tumah, It's only as
I'm removing it that it no longer is a source of the
limb and no longer the source of טומאה tumah. that you could
say it receives טומאה tumah from the limb itself. But it's not—where
is it touching the limb? It's touching the limb at the point
that I'm cutting it away, right at the point of contact. That
point of attachment is not yet an exposed part. So if something
touches in a non-exposed part of itself, normally that would say, for
example, let's say a human being touched by something inside the inside
his or her mouth. Okay, so that's not exposed, that's not considered
touch. Touch has to be an exposed part of you, not a
hidden part of you. So here, if after you cut it away,
after that place of connection is exposed, it's no longer touching. It's
only touching before it's exposed. So that is not considered to be
touching and therefore how did it transfer טומאה? tumah. That was my
question. Now sometimes the גמרא Gemara says that it really doesn't have
to transfer through touch. The fact that it went through this transition,
it was a source of טומאה tumah. and then it became food,
so it transitioned—it's like something touches itself. You know what I'm saying?
So what's left from having transitioned is at least it was related,
connected to its previous identity to have this remnant of טומאה. tumah
But here it's understanding that it really is through some sense of
touching and he says the touching was it was unexposed surface. So
why did that transfer טומאה? tumah So אמר ליה, Amar lei, that
was what רבי אסי asked רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira said, אפילו לדידי קשיא, afilu lidi kashya, you know what? I
was bothered by the exact same thing yesterday in the בית מדרש.
ושאלתיה לרבי אבא בר ממל, V'shailyi l'Rabbi Abba bar Mamal, so I
asked Rabbi Abba bar Mamal this question: I don't get how it
transfers when you cut away this piece of meat. ואמר לי V'amar
li and he said to me, הני רבי מאיר היא, hanni Rabbi
Meir hi, this is the position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, this
ברייתא, braita. דאמר טומאת בית הסתרים מטמאה d'amar tumas beis hastarim metamei
that says that it can transfer טומאה Tumah, even when it is
in this non-exposed part. Now what is רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Of
course you will remember—I'm joking a little bit, but
anyway—about only about seventy pages ago when maybe sixty pages ago, you
remember?
I remember something of this same question. Really?
A good. Okay, it was the fetus that stuck its arm out,
remember the fetus that stuck out its arm? Right. Well, let's say
it did bring it back. So then you שחט shecht the בהמה.
beheima. So that case we consider the arm to be a נבילה,
neveila, not the שחיטה shechita didn't apply to it. So the arm
is a source of טומאה. Tumah Now you cut it away from
the fetus that was in the womb. Okay, is the fetus טמא
tamei because it was in contact with the arm that was part
of the body? And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says yes, it was
in contact with that arm that was part of the body, it
became טמא. tamei And there it's interesting because there the fetus itself
was never the source of טומאה, Tumah it's even weaker than our
case where the actual meat was at one point the source. But
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says since it was in contact with its
own limb. But its contact with its own limb was not on
an exposed surface and nevertheless it transferred טומאה. Tumah? So he says
that's who it's going like, it's going like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
So אמר ליה, amar leh, what?
That was seventy pages ago.
About. So time flies when you're having fun, maybe sixty. Okay so
anyway, so אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי אסי said to רבי
זירא—רבי זירא said, oh yeah, I asked that question—but so רבי אסי
said אמר ליה זיל בזמנין סגיאין אמרה קמאי, amar lei zil bazimnin
sagi'in amrah kammai,
one minute, you let him get away with that? Many times רבי
אבא בר ממל Rabbi Abba bar Mamal tried to say the same
thing to me when I was around ואמרי ליה, v'amri lei, but
I said back to him, שאני ליה לרבי מאיר בין טומאה דבעיא
הכשר בין טומאה דלא בעיא הכשר, shanni lei l'Rabbi Meir bein tumah
d'ba'ya hachshar bein tumah d'lo ba'ya hachshar,
one minute, you can't compare the case. There there is no need
for הכשר. hachshar. Why was there no need for הכשר? hachshar? Because
the fetus, if you remember, when you שחט shecht an animal, there's
no need for it to become in contact with liquid for it
to be הוכשר, huchshar, the שחיטה shechita makes it fit. Okay, so
there okay, maybe it can transfer without an exposed surface, but at
least the fetus is susceptible for טומאה. Tumah, In our case, the
meat that you are pulling away, it was it was never susceptible
because there was no שחיטה shechita that made it permissible. It was
part of an אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai So that meat,
there's another problem: before that it's—besides that it's not touching an exposed
surface, it never came in contact with liquid and is never susceptible.
So actually it's funny that he was so objected this answer because
the question he was asking that it didn't touch an exposed surface
you actually got a good answer to. There's a position of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that says when you cut it away it doesn't
matter if it didn't touch an exposed surface. He just really has
another problem which is: there it didn't need הכשר. hachshar. Here the
piece of meat needed הכשר, hachshar, needed to come in contact with
liquid and that didn't happen. So I don't understand how it works
even even regardless of the issue of touching a non-exposed surface.
We discussed something the other day about the the blood of the
שחיטה shechita makes it הוכשר.
huchshar. Yes, and that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir case about the fetus,
but here it is—here it is an—אבר מן החי, eiver min ha-chai,
a limb that dropped away when it was alive, so it never
had the act of שחיטה, shechita, it never had the blood of
שחיטה. shechita. Right, that's why in our case he says this meat,
even if you're not bothered by the fact that the contact was
non-exposed surface. The problem is that the meat was never in contact
with liquid to become susceptible. So he says, still doesn't answer the
question. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said, "My קושיא,
kushya, why is that such a problem? דנימא דהוכשר, De-neima de-huchshar,
that's your whole issue? Fine, we'll say the case is that it
did come in contact with liquid. Okay, so now of course part
of the problem is if you remember, the גמרא Gemara had a
discussion before, does the coming in contact with liquid have to follow
your defining it as food, or can it come before defining it
as food? Here, you would have to assert, and this is probably
why it bothered him, that it had to precede the defining it
as food, because here it says, well, maybe not, but you know
the point is that you'd have to make it that you plan
on eating the meat, then it came in contact with liquid, then
you tore the meat away. Okay, and that would—that would be the
circumstances. Okay, but that's the only way to explain that ברייתא. Braisa.
Now, אמר ליה רבא בר רב חנאן לרבא, Amar lei Rava bar
Rav Chanan le-Rava, למה לי הכשר? Lama li hechshar?
He said, I got a better answer to this question. We dealt
with one issue that it's non-exposed surface, we said there's רבי מאיר'ס
Rabbi Meir's position. Now we're dealing with another problem, that this piece
of meat never came in contact with liquid or we didn't assert
that it did. Why is that an issue? We don't need to
worry about that. Why not? הרי
מטמא טומאה חמורה אגב אביו. Harei metamei tumah chamurah agav aviv. There's
a principle that you'll remember—maybe remember this from a previous דף—that something
that eventually, normally we say eventually, but here we're going to say
in the past, but something that will become a higher
source of—טומאה חמורה, tumah chamurah, a weighty טומאה, Tumah. a source of
טומאה Tumah. in the future does not need הכשר hechshar to become
susceptible. This thing right now, we want it to be considered food.
We want it to become in contact with liquid in order to
make it susceptible for טומאה. Tumah But what we say is is
that if it will become actually a worse טומאה Tumah in the
future, a source of טומאה Tumah. in the future, then the fact
that it's going to even be a source of טומאה, tumah, a
weightier טומאה, tumah means it doesn't need that liquid to make it
susceptible right now. Normally we say that if something is going to
be in the future a source of טומאה, tumah? but here we're
saying it in the past. This piece of meat was cut away
from a limb, an אבר מן החי. eiver min ha-chai. When it
was part of the limb, it was a source of טומאה. tumah
So if something started its life—usually we say in the future, but
this is even better—if it started its life as the source of
טומאה, tumah then you don't need it to have this הכשר hechshar
to make it susceptible for טומאה. tumah. It was already, you know,
very much part of the world of טומאה, tumah, so even without
the liquid, the הכשר, hechshar, it will be susceptible. So we have
two answers. What about the problem it never touched something with an
exposed surface? That's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. What about the problem that
it never came in contact with liquid, this piece of meat? Who
needs it to be הוכשר? huchshar? It was already the source of
טומאה. tumah, Who needs it to, you know, who needs it to
become in contact with liquid to get into that category? Okay, so
that's what he says.
Why don't we just
say, you know, when
you're cutting it, you know, presumably some of the blood of whatever
it is that, you know...
Because only דם שחיטה dam shechita is מכשיר, machshir, not דם מכה.
dam makah. So that would not be considered דם שחיטה dam shechita
from normal blood that runs out.
Yeah, but it's such a romantic, if it was a מכה, makah,
if it was like a cold, but it's just a normal, like,
it's just in terms of maybe the volume
of blood, because it may be more of a—like it's like a—you
might interpret it as being for a cut, but it's just a—when
you cut yourself, like, you get a certain amount of blood.
Yeah, but that's what I said to Michael, that only blood of
שחיטה shechita causes הכשר. hechshar.
Any other blood, unless for like, you know, if a person is
killed, that's דם חללים, dam chalalim, is a different category. But generally
types of normal cuts or whatever, yeah, don't count.
Okay, so let's just, you know, this interpreted.
Okay, yeah. Alright, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So
אמר ליה רבא—so ומה קושיא
דנימא דהוכשר. u-mah kushya de-neima de-huchshar. אמר ליה רבא בר רב חנאן
לרבא, Amar lei Rava bar Rav Chanan le-Rava, למה לי הכשר? Lama
li hechshar? Why do I need it? הרי מטמא טומאה חמורה אגב
אביו. Harei metamei tumah chamurah agav aviv. It started as a weighty
טומאה tumah, by its father, meaning when it was part of the
limb. So now that it's cut as a piece of meat, it
shouldn't even need הכשר. hechshar. If the touch happens through the non-exposed
surface and the הכשר hechshar is not necessary because it was a
source of טומאה. tumah אמר ליה, so he said, no, no, no,
I don't like that answer. Why don't I like that answer? Because
כששימש מעשה עץ שימש. Keshe-shimesh ma'aseh etz shimesh. When it was serving
the father, when it was serving its original limb, it was functioning
there, forget that phrasing, it was functioning there as a piece of
wood. Now what does that mean, a piece of wood? Well, a,
right, it can't be eaten. Meaning exactly that. That here, when you
take away the piece of meat and you want it to become—now
you want—asking will it become טמא, tamei, what category are you going
to say it will become טמא? tamei, As food. Food is susceptible
to טומאה. tumah When it was part of the limb, it wasn't
functioning as food and it was a different identity. Now why wasn't
it functioning as food? רש"י Rashi first of all says because it's
forbidden to eat an אבר מן החי. eiver min ha-chai. That's true,
and you hadn't yet to define it as food subjectively, it's always
objectively forbidden. But the other reason is, and רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot both say this, the reason אבר מן החי ever min hachai
is a source of טומאה tumah, has nothing to do with its
identity as food. The
conceptually it being a source of טומאה tumah was not because it
was defined as food because what do you need for an אבר?
You also need the bone and you need the ligaments. So what
defines it as an אבר had to do with its identity as
a limb, not its identity. identity of food. So it's not exactly
wood, עץ, Etz, but the point is it's a completely different categorization
and identity of it. So yes, it was a source of טומאה,
tumah but that was when it had a different identity. That when
its identity was as limb. Now that the significance identity for טומאה
tumah. purposes is food, that's a new identity, רש"י Rashi. uses the
phrase פנים חדשות באו לכאן, Panim Chadashot Ba'u Lechan, a new face
has come here, a new identity, and therefore as food it never
was the source of טומאה tumah, and that's why we're assuming it
needs הכשר. Hechsher. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to go
through about till the bottom of the page about five more cases
like this where we're saying why does something need הכשר, Hechsher, wasn't
it a source of טומאה? tumah And the answer will be no,
that's when it had a different identity.
מעשה עץ כמי שהיה, Ma'aseh Etz Kimei Shehayah, it was functioning as
wood. Doesn't literally mean wood, but it means it was not functioning
as food. Its identity was different and therefore it's not relevant. Yes.
We can't eat אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, non-Jews can't eat
it, can they be fed to animals?
No, you can't get הנאה.
Hana'ah. No הנאה, Hana'ah, that's right.
So we're going to talk at the bottom of the page that
therefore it might not be able to become טמא tamei. as food
regardless because if it's physically possible to eat but not הלכתית Halachically
possible to eat. That'll be a question at the end. We are
now assuming that אבר מן החי ever min hachai that it can
be a source of טומאה, tumah this בשר מן החי. Basar Min
HaChai Because you can't and it's... what? Because you can't and it's...
physically you can eat it. It's fit to be eaten at a
physical level even if not at a הלכתית Halachic level. Yes.
Or wouldn't it be waste? I mean what could you do with
it if you were...
Right, you'd have to waste it. Yeah, like there are some things
that are forbidden in הנאה Hana'ah and you have to just burn
them and destroy them. Absolutely. Okay.
Can
anybody eat the meat if it wasn't a whole אבר?
No, בשר מן החי Basar Min HaChai is forbidden to... that we
are talking again to remind us, אבר מן החי ever min hachai,
is a source of טומאה. tumah You take away the meat, the
question is does the meat become טמא tamei, because בשר מן החי
Basar Min HaChai, is not a source of טומאה. tumah? But בשר
מן החי, basar min ha-chai. meat is still forbidden to be eaten
by Jews and non-Jews and so on. So that's the question, it's
not הלכתית Halachically able to be eaten, but we're still calling it
food because physically it can be and benefit.
Exactly.
Well, can you really bury it in the ground as fertilizer?
Right, well, okay, if it's maybe the desert somewhere. Anyway, let's go
on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, so now we're going to have a couple of cases just
like this. הרי אמרו Harei Amru they said, קופת שאור Kupat Se'or
שייחדה לישיבה, Sheyichdah liyeshivah, you've got a kneading trough, I don't exactly
know what a קופה Kupah is, some type of obviously some type
of a large thing that I think it's some type of a
kneading trough that you use sourdough in, that you kneaded sourdough. How
do they translate it? Leaven. No, I know what sourdough is. Okay,
שאור. Se'or. קופת. Kupat. A block.
A block? That's what it says, a block. B-L-O-C-K.
B-L-O-C-K, yes.
A block of leaven. That's strange.
Oh, that you took, really? I thought it meant, okay, fine. What?
All right,
so that's actually understanding it. Hold on a second, let me check
רש"י.
Rashi's
It says רש"י Rashi in two places.
מוטיו. Mutyo. All right, we'll use it with that. All right, fine,
yeah, exactly. All right, let's go with that. There's another case actually
that deals with a kneading trough, but we'll go with that. So
you've got something, either it is a כלי Kli that is used
for that used for sourdough or שאור, Se'or, which is, you know,
which is obviously a type of a חמץ, Chametz, or that actually
is a whole big block and hardened block of this thing itself.
Okay. שייחדה לישיבה, Sheyichdah liyeshivah, now you designate it to be a
chair to sit on it. So basically you've changed its purpose, okay,
and you're now going to just sit on this big hardened block
of sourdough or on this kneading or on this some type of
a vessel that has in its crevices these pieces of sourdough, okay,
but I will defer to the explanation of a block. Okay, so
בטלה טומאתו, Batlah Tumato, so בטלה. Batlah. So that is negated. It's
no longer is considered food and because it's no longer considered food,
A, you don't transgress on פסח Pesach because it's just considered now
a piece of furniture, and B, presumably because it's considered to be
now a seat, it can become טמא. tamei, A זב Zav can
sit on it. If a זב Zav sits on it, then it
becomes טמא. tamei. Okay, so it's not a חמץ Chametz problem and
it is a טומאה tumah problem. So he so the גמרא Gemara
says, so says אביי, Abaye, טומאתו לאו דאורייתא. Tumato Lav De'oraita. The
that טומאה tumah of it being the considered a vessel and a
seat is not biblical. How do I know? דאי סלקא דעתך דאורייתא,
De'i Salka Da'atach De'oraita, were it biblical, מצינו לאוכלים שמטמאים טומאה חמורה.
Matzinu Le'ochlim Shemetam'im Tumah Chamurah. So then how could I say ever
that food needs to come in contact with liquid? Because I can
always say that any food has the potential of getting stale and
hard and turning it into a seat.
So how would food ever need to come in contact with liquid?
It could always in the future be a source of טומאה. tumah
Now of course, first of all, there's an obvious difference which is,
well, there are two obvious differences. Number one, maybe certain types of
food is more likely to be used in that purpose than others.
You know, you can't necessarily make vegetables into a seat, maybe you
can make a hardened piece of dough into a seat. The other
point is is that maybe this idea that it doesn't need הכשר
Hechsher is only when it definitely was or is... inevitably will be
a source of טומאה, tumah. not just when it theoretically is possible.
But that's what אביי Abaye assumes, that the theoretical possibility should be
enough, and therefore he says that can only be rabbinic, that it's
becomes really considered a seat and the source of טומאה tumah. and
as because right. And actually, thank you Charlie, why is it considered
to be a weightier טומאה? tumah If it's a seat, it's a
vessel, it can also receive טומאה tumah like food, but why is
it weightier? It's weightier for exactly what Charlie said, because if it's
a seat and a זב zav sits on it, then when a
זב zav sits on a seat, it not only is considered a
ראשון, rishon, something that's derived טומאה tumah from the זב, zav, but
it's considered an אב, av, a source of טומאה. tumah, So he,
אביי Abaye is saying, the principle being that if food was in
the past or in the future will be a source of טומאה,
tumah it never requires הכשר. hechsher. So says אביי, Abaye, why does
any food require הכשר? hechsher? You could always turn it into a
seat, a זב zav could sit on it, it could be the
source of טומאה, tumah and since it could be the source of
טומאה, tumah it would never require it, assuming that the theoretical possibility
is enough to say it doesn't require הכשר. hechsher. That's אביי's Abaye
question. So therefore the idea that it is considered a seat and
able to become a source of טומאה tumah is only rabbinic. Let's
see what the answer is. So it says, the גמרא Gemara says
the answer that it's going to say again and again, פירשו משום
מעשה עץ. pirshu mishum ma'aseh etz. No, even if it becomes a
seat, that's serving as a piece of wood. Here the idea wood
works a lot better because that's what you make seats out of.
So what it's saying is is that no, it might be able
to be a source of טומאה tumah as a seat, but then
it stops, it loses its old identity. It no longer is food.
Then it actually is wood and a seat, and therefore that has
no relevance to its status now as food. Now as food does
it require הכשר? hechsher? Yes. Ah, maybe it'll be a source of
טומאה, tumah then it won't be food. But as its identity of
food, it will never be a source of טומאה tumah. and therefore
it requires הכשר. hechsher. Yes, Michael.
Isn't there some kind of respect issue in terms of respect towards
food? You know, we've brought up with that,
you know, like...
It's a good question. Yeah, I don't know. I mean again, if
it gets hardened and not really usable for something else, you know,
it's a different story. But it is a good question and our
גמרא Gemara is particularly in relation to bread, to figure out how
we're supposed to treat bread. Yeah, so I'll have to get, you
know, I'll have to think about this more. Now תוספות Tosafot asks
a question. תוספות Tosafot says how could we even think that it's
not biblical, then how are you allowed to own it on פסח?
Pesach? Okay, and right, the whole reason you're allowed to own it
on פסח Pesach is because it stops being considered food. But there
presumably is an answer, there could be a middle category. Could be,
a, you know, if you're presumably it's hard enough to not be
so usable anyway. It's some type of a state where the objective
reality and your subjective definition are enough to say that it's no
longer considered חמץ. chametz. But אביי's Abaye point could have been, fine,
it's one thing to say it stops being food, it's another thing
to say that it really has the status of a chair and
it really has the status of a vessel. So it's possible that
there's a middle category. But anyway תוספות Tosafot raises that challenge. So
again the question is if something will be, was or will be
a source of טומאה tumah. does it need הכשר? hechsher? Why is
it all food that way? And the answer is because even if
you were to somehow refashion food into some type of a seat,
that would be a totally new identity and it's not relevant for
now. Yes, Charlie.
I was going to say that the חמץ chametz is אסור בהנאה
assur behana'ah and it actually is still in a certain respect חמץ.
chametz.
Right. Even if it's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah that makes it, right,
stop being food. It is the fact that, well, that's an interesting
point. I mean certainly foods that are אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah would
be circular to say that they get out of that category through
being אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. That is true. Okay, the question about
an אבר מן החי ever min hachai is different because there we're
looking in through a different lens, not through the lens of being
forbidden, but through the lens of, anyway, that issue has yet to
be raised, Charlie. We'll get to it at the bottom of the
page. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Let's look
at another couple of cases. Okay, yeah. Okay, so let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. אביי Abaye
has a couple of questions like this with all the same answer.
הרי אמרו, Harei amru, they said, תקרובת עבודה זרה tikrovet avodah zarah
של אוכלין shel ochlin מטמאין באהל. metam'in b'ohel.
Let's say you took a little food and somebody offered it up
to the Buddha, okay, or whatever, you know, to a god, to
Zeus, okay, then it becomes forbidden as an offering to an idol.
Now that is, we said yesterday, we mentioned that עבודה זרה avodah
zarah and offerings to עבודה זרה avodah zarah are a source of
טומאה. tumah. And as a source of טומאה, tumah. it's even טומאה
tumah, like a מת meit and would cause טומאה tumah. to anything
under the same roof, מטמאין באהל. metam'in b'ohel. Now we've got a
question because here you have food, any food can become the source
of טומאה tumah, if you offered it to an idol, okay? So
why don't we say that food never needs to come in contact
with a liquid because you could always turn it into a source
of טומאה? tumah. Again, אביי Abaye is assuming that it's the potential
of being a source of טומאה tumah, even if it's not inevitable
or likely. So אביי Abaye says טומאתה לאו דאורייתא. tumatah lav d'oraita.
That טומאה tumah. of offerings to עבודה זרה avodah zarah is not
biblical. דאי סלקא דעתך דאורייתא, De'i salka datchach d'oraita,
if you were to say it's biblical, משכחת לה לאוכלין דמטמאי טומאה
חמורה. mashkachat lah l'ochlin d'metam'ei tumah chamurah.
You see that food can become a source of טומאה tumah. and
then food would never have to come in contact with liquid. And
we know that's not true. And again assuming that the theoretical possibility
is enough to say it doesn't require it. And the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara's* answer is the same: תשמיש מצאו ועשאו תשמיש *tishmesh matzao ve-asao
tishmesh*. No. In that other capacity it's acting as wood. Now that's
a little bit more of a surprising answer because you would think
when something is being offered to an idol, if it's let's say
food, it's offered as food. Here is the food to this god.
But presumably the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's* understanding is that it's not necessarily
so because it's offered more as a gift. Its identity of food
is not per se
important. You could offer jewelry to the idol, you could offer vessels
to the idol. Food is only one type of a thing that
you're offering, so it's there, its identity really is more as a
gift to the idol, not as food per se. And therefore it
would not have that sort sense of source of טומאה tumah. *tumah*
as food. The source of טומאה tumah. *tumah* is coming from its
identity as an offering, as a gift and not per se as
food. Although that is the one that is sort of much closer
to the idea of food than anything else. I will say that
in general this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* aside, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in
שבת *Shabbos* deals with idols as a source of טומאה tumah? *tumah*
and the conclusion there is that it is rabbinic. But the point
here is that there is no evidence from that because here it's
a different identity. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on
same type of thing a couple of times. Where are we? אמר
אביי הרי אמרו harei amru, *Amar Abaye harei amru*, here's another case.
They said חיבורי אוכלין ככלים דמו *chiburei ochlin ke-keilim damu*. If things
that are attached to food are like vessels. Meaning let's say you've
got a vessel and it's got crusted on remnants of food on
it. And you go ahead and you touch this food gook that's
on the surface of the vessel. So that basically becomes secondary to
the vessel itself and it becomes like the very vessel itself, like
you touched the vessel. Okay so if that's true, that's food, the
gunk on it, then it's going to be like the vessel, and
that has now the potential of being a source of טומאה tumah
*tumah*. Why? Because he says like this. One minute, let me just
see what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says here. Let me just check רש"י
*Rashi* out for a second.
Ah okay right. רש"י *Rashi* has a better example by the way
than I do, which is not just the stuff that is
one minute right not just the stuff that's like the gook on
the surface of the כלי *kli*, but it's actually food that serves
a function within the כלי *kli*, that it actually is integrated in
the כלי *kli*. So let's say you have cracks and this was
more what I was saying before which was the קופח *kupach* case
but it presumably isn't. Anyway you have cracks in a vessel, let's
say, and you have food gets into the cracks. So it gets
into the cracks, it's actually becoming part of one with the כלי
*kli*, maybe even doing a good job of sealing the surface of
the כלי *kli*. So that type of a case the food is
considered like the vessel itself. Now how could a vessel become more
טמא tamei *tamei* than food? More weightier than
food? Because they can both receive טומאה tumah. *tumah*. How is a
vessel more weightier? So it's more weightier if it touches let's say
a מת mais *meis*, a corpse. A corpse is considered an אבי
אבות *avi avos*, the granddaddy of טומאות *tumos*. When a vessel touches
it, it is an אב הטומאה av hatumah, *av ha-tumah*. Okay now
food is never an אב הטומאה av hatumah, *av ha-tumah*, never is
the highest level. But as now integrated into the vessel and if
the vessel touched the מת mais, *meis*, it would be considered an
אב הטומאה *av ha-tumah*. So here he's saying any food can at
one stage in its life become an אב הטומאה *av ha-tumah* if
it gets into the cracks of a vessel and that vessel now
touches a corpse. Okay? So any food can become a weighty טומאה
tumah *tumah*, it shouldn't need contact with liquid. Okay? So he says
הרי אמרו חיבורי אוכלין ככלים דמו *harei amru chiburei ochlin ke-keilim damu*.
The things that adhere to vessels are like vessels, and therefore the
food inside of it becomes like the vessel itself. So טומאתם לאו
דאורייתא *tumasam lav de-oraysa*, it can't be biblical, דאי סלקא דעתך דאורייתא
*di-salka da'atach de-oraysa*, if you think it's biblical, מצינו לאוכל שמטמא טומאה
tumah. חמורה *matzinu le-ochel she-metamei tumah chamurah*. So then you see food
can actually be a source an אב הטומאה *av ha-tumah* and therefore
should never require הכשר hechsher. *hechsher*. So the answer of course is
the same: תשמיש מצאו ועשאו תשמיש *tishmesh matzao ve-asao tishmesh*. No, if
it becomes into the vessel then it's serving like a piece of
wood. There you really understand that metaphor. It's a piece of wood,
it's not its identity as food. It's like its identity as
putty. It's serving as a filler for the holes and not its
identity of food, so that's not relevant. Okay, we are not yet
done. Yes? Yes?
I'm sorry, I just something you said earlier is bothering me and
I don't know if it's my ignorance or what. I never ever
viewed Buddha as a god.
Oh yeah I that's why I didn't
want to All
right, all right, all right, all right and that's why you said
Zeus. Wait, wait, wait.
That means it is not עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*. He he was
a prince who was the source of knowledge. And I really think
it's not right to put that across the table.
That's why Okay, Bobby, you are absolutely correct, which is why I
immediately corrected myself after saying that and you were so upset and
anyway and I and I
changed it to.
There is an interesting question, I don't know if you noticed that,
but there it raised- there is interesting questions around Buddha and attitudes
towards Buddhism and how the religion is defined by sort of the
leadership and how it's practiced by the laity. So it raises a
lot of interesting questions. And הלכה halacha? has dealt a lot more
in its 2000 years with Christianity and Islam and there is very
little הלכתי halachic treatment of the eastern religions and how to categorize
them. So you make an excellent point and to avoid that issue
I immediately revised it. But okay, no no, you are correct to
raise that issue. Back to what? Back to the tape. Back to
being pieces of wood. Let's go on. So אמר ליה רב פפא
לרבא Amrei lei Rav Papa l'Rava or Papa said to Rava, everybody's
getting on the bandwagon now. Okay, הא דתניא, Ha d'tanya, that which
we taught in a ברייתא. braita: חלב נבילה, Chelev neveila, remember the
fat of animals, which is considered more food in the city than
it is in the villages? So we're back to that. You have
fat of a
נבילה. neveila. We'll see why it has to be a נבילה neveila
in a minute. So normally it would not be considered food because
it's בכפרים, bakfarim, it's in the villages. צריך מחשבה והכשר. Tzarich machshava
v'hechsher.
You need to designate it as food, plan to eat it, because
normally it would not be assumed to be food in the villages,
and then it needs to come in contact with liquid. So he
says, טומאתו אגב כוליה לאו דאורייתא. Tumaso agav kulya lav d'oraisa. He
says one minute, a classic place of the source of חלב chelev
is the חלב chelev that's around the kidneys. So if you take
a lump of חלב chelev with the kidneys embedded inside, the kidney
is a נבילה, neveila, right? Because this is of an animal that
wasn't שחט. shachted. The kidney is a source of טומאה. tumah So
now this חלב, chelev, but what's the הלכה? halacha If you touch
the חלב, chelev, you're טמא tamei like you touched the kidney. Okay,
why? Like you touched the נבילה. neveila. Now that's because of a
principle we learned before, which is שומר. shomer. The חלב chelev protects
the kidney, it's a שומר shomer to the kidney, so if you
touch the חלב chelev it's like you touched the kidney and you're
טמא. tamei But that is effectively the חלב chelev then is a
source of טומאה. tumah. It's as bad as touching the kidney itself.
So why if I remove the חלב chelev and I plan on
eating it, why do I need it to come in contact with
liquid? It once when it started life, and here it started life,
it's not just a potential future, when it started life it was
an actual source of טומאה tumah. when it was connected to the
kidney. So it should not require הכשר. hechsher. So he says, טומאתו
אגב כוליה לאו דאורייתא. Tumaso agav kulya lav d'oraisa. Should
we have to say that the טומאה tumah. of that חלב chelev
when it's connected to the kidney is not biblical? ואי סלקא דעתך
דאורייתא, V'isalka deitach d'oraisa, if you think it's biblical, מצינו לאוכל שמתמא
טומאה חמורה. matzinu l'ochel shemetamei tuma chamura.
We see that food, it originally and here originally
it was a source of טומאה tumah. when it was connected to
the kidney and therefore it should not require coming in contact with
liquid after it's separated. So he says, no, כששימש מעשה עץ שימש.
k'shimesh maaseh etz shimesh. Same answer, there it was like wood, and
here you really could say wood, because there its reason it was
טמא tamei. was not as food, the reason the חלב chelev was
טמא tamei when it was connected to the kidney was that it
was a שומר. shomer. A classic שומר shomer is like the shell
around a nut, it's a thing, it's to be like wood. Okay,
so it's not because of identity as food. So the גמרא Gemara
introduces this idea that if something started its life as a weighty
טומאה, tumah a source of, an אב הטומאה, or it will become
an אב הטומאה, then when it's food it doesn't require הכשר. hechsher?
So it gave a whole list of examples where that can be.
It started it that way or will end that way, so why
does it require הכשר? hechsher. And the answer in all those cases
is, no no no, in those cases when
it's a source of טומאה tumah it's because of its different identity,
not its identity as food. So somebody should be asking me, so
is there ever any case where this is a relevant law? So
the one case where this is a relevant law is the idea
of a טומאת נבילת עוף טהור, tumas neveilas of tahor, נבילת עוף
טהור. neveilas of tahor. A נבילה neveila of a כשר kosher bird
or of a chicken does not cause טומאה tumah. by touching it.
It does cause טומאה tumah when you eat it, when you swallow
it. So there the הלכה is, if that dead chicken comes in
contact with something טמא, tamei. it does not require הכשר. hechsher. It
is food, fit to be eaten, it will become, it has the
potential of being a source of טומאה tumah when I eat it,
but then it's a source of טומאה tumah. as food, because it's
when I eat it. So therefore now as food it doesn't require
הכשר. hechshar. That is the one application of the law, but all
the other cases when it's a source of טומאה tumah. it's not
through its identity as food. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר רב מתנא, amar Rav Masna, הרי אמרו, they said,
בית שטיחו בזרעים טהרו. bayis shetikho b'zraim taharu. Okay, so if you
basically took some type of seeds, now you can't actually do seeds
but רש''י says like seeds inside of their husks, inside of their...
so you took like wheat stalks, barley stalks that have the seeds
still in them and you threw it up on your roof and
you plan to use it as your roof. So then if they
were טמא, tamei. now that they've become part of your roof they
become טהור. tahor They are like something attached to the ground, they
lose their past identity. But because they're part of the house they
can also be a source of טומאה tumah. *tumah*. How? If the
house gets צרעת tzara'at, *tzaraat*, then they become a source of טומאה
tumah. *tumah*. And that's the weighty טומאה tumah. *tumah*, that's an אב
הטומאה *av hatumah*. So he says טומאת אהלו *tumas ohalo* דאורייתא *d'oraisa*.
That idea that they can become a source of טומאה tumah. *tumah*
now that they're part of the house can't be biblical. Why? דאי
סלקא דעתך *di salka dach* דאורייתא *d'oraisa*, if it's biblical, מצינו דזרעים
שמטמאין טומאה tumah, חמורה *matzinu d'zraim shemetamei tumah chamura*, then any normal
wheat seed could in the end be a source of טומאה tumah.
*tumah* and therefore should never require contact with liquid. So how come
how can they require contact with liquid? It must be this whole
idea is not biblical when they become a when they're become part
of the house. And he says no, כששימש מעץ שימש *k'shimesh me'eitz
shimesh* again, same old answer. That is a different identity. When they're
the roof and they become טמא tamei *tamei* as the roof of
a house that has צרעת *tzaraat*, that is not as food that
they're טמא tamei *tamei*, they're טמא tamei. *tamei* there as wood as
part of the roof. So most of your all of these questions
other than the one example of the dead bird, all of these
cases that them being a source of טומאה *tumah* is when they
don't have the identity of food and therefore it's not relevant to
them being able to be susceptible for טומאה *tumah* as food. Interesting
parenthetical point, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* lists the case of הרי אמרו
*harei amru*. רש"י *Rashi* says I have no idea where they said
this. In all of the other cases they were quoting משניות mishnayot
*Mishnas*, maybe a ברייתא braisa *Braisa*, but this last case, if you'll
see there's no cross-reference for it and it's one of those interesting
places where רש"י *Rashi* says I don't know where the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s getting this from because you know he's quoting something as if
it's an accepted ruling. Okay, now we finally move on to the
last statement of the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*, which is רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, the dangling limb. Remember, dangling limb, while it's on
the animal, it's food. When the animal is shechted, then it's considered
to be, so then it is food also susceptible for טומאה *tumah*.
The only question is is whether it needs to have הכשר hechshar.
*hechshir*, whether it needs additional הכשר hechshar. *hechshir* or the שחיטה shechita
*shechita* was enough for the הכשר *hechshir*. If the animal dies, then
it's like it fell off in the animal's life and then it
is a אבר מן החי ever min hachai *eiver min hachai*. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon* says and it says it's טהור tahor,
*tahor*. Now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s first question is going to be
why is it טהור tahor *tahor*? Make up your mind. If it's
like it fell off when the animal died, it's אבר מן החי
ever min hachai, *eiver min hachai*. If it's like it didn't fall
off, so the animal that died is a נבלה *neveilah*. Either way,
this dangling limb has to be טמא tamei, *tamei*. How could you
say it's completely טהור tahor *tahor*? So let's take a look. מן
דשך *man d'shach*, which means what's your desire, literally מן דשכך *man
d'shachah*, what's your desire, but really means like either way this doesn't
make sense. אי מיתה עושה ניפול *ie misa osah nipul*, if the
death of the animal makes it like the limb fell off, this
dangling limb, ליטמא משום אבר מן החי *litamei mishum eiver min hachai*.
So it should be טמא tamei, *tamei* because of an אבר מן
החי *eiver min hachai*. אי אין מיתה עושה ניפול *ie ein misa
osah nipul*, if the death is not like it fell off, so
it's like it died with the limb attached, so ליטמא משום אבר
מן הנבלה *litamei mishum eiver min haneveilah*. Fine, so the whole animal's
a נבלה *neveilah*, let it be a נבלה *neveilah*. So how does
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon* say it's totally טהור tahor. *tahor*?
So גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon ארישא קאי *Rabbi
Shimon areisha kai*. Yeah, yeah, when it says at the end of
the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says it's
טהור tahor, *tahor*, he's not talking about the last case, he's going
back to the first case of the dangling limb when the animal
was still alive. What is the first case? האבר והבשר המדולדלין בבהמה
*ha'eiver vehabasar hameduldalin bibeheimah*, a limb or meat that's dangling in the
animal, מטמאין טומאת אוכלין במקומן *metamei tumas ochlin bimkoman*, they're considered food
and can become susceptible while they're still there, וצריכין הכשר *vetzrichin hechshir*,
and they need to come in contact with liquid. ורבי שמעון מטהר
v'Rebbe Shimon metaher. *verabbi Shimon metaher*. This dangling limb while the animal
is alive, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says is טהור tahor,
*tahor*. Why? Why does he say it's טהור tahor? *tahor*? So אמר
*Amar* because meaning it's not considered food. Okay, it can't be considered
food this dangling limb while the animal is alive. Why? And now
we get Charlie what Charlie's been saying. אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן Amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan. *Amar Rav Assi Amar Rabbi
Yochanan*, מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון mai taama d'Rabbi Shimon? *mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Shimon*, what's the reason רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says that
this dangling limb cannot be food and cannot become טמא *tamei*? אמר
קרא amar kra, *Amar kra*, the verse says, מכל האוכל אשר יאכל
mi-kol ha-ochel asher ye'achel, *mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel*, from all food that
will be eaten, if it comes in contact with a טמא *tamei*
thing it will become טמא *tamei*. אוכל שאתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים קרוי
אוכל ochel she-ata yachol le'achilo l'acherim karui ochel, *ochel she'atah yachol lehachilo
l'acherim kari ochel*. Food that either you can eat or you can
feed to others, halachically you can eat or feed to others, so
it doesn't have to be kosher food, but it has to be
at least be something that a non-Jew could eat and something you
can get benefits from. You could offer it to a non-Jew. Then
that's food, קרוי אוכל *kari ochel*. אוכל שאי אתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים
*ochel she'ee atah yachol lehachilo l'acherim*, food that you cannot feed it
to others, non-Jews can't eat it and you can't derive benefit from
it, אין קרוי אוכל *ein kari ochel*, it's not food. Now this
answer won't help when the animal dies because then it's still an
אבר מן החי *eiver min hachai* or an נבלה *neveilah*, it doesn't
need to be called food. But when the animal is alive and
the limb is dangling and the only way that it can become
טמא *tamei* is as food, so he says I'm not prepared to
call that food. I won't call something that is dangling, it's not
yet an אבר מן החי *eiver min hachai*, it's not a source
of טומאה *tumah*, but what's the reason to call it food? Because
you could say theoretically I could yank this limb off of the
animal and I could eat it. And that's why you're going to
call it food. Remember, the dangling limb while the animal's alive. So
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says you can't call it food
because of that because you can't yank it off and use it
because you can't eat it and a non-Jew can't eat it. So
therefore I'm not prepared to call this dangling limb food, it's not
possible to eat. Okay, אמרי לה רבי זירא לרב אסי *amrei leh
Rabbi Zeira l'Rabbi Assi*, some say רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* said to
רב אסי *Rabbi Assi*, דילמא טעמא דרבי שמעון התם משום מעורה מעורה
*dilma ta'ama d'Rabbi Shimon hasham mishum me'ura me'ura*. How do you know
that the logic behind saying a dangling limb while the animal is
alive is not food has to be the fancy explanation that it's
not permissible to be eaten? Maybe It's a much more simple thing:
since it's still intertwined, it's like it's one unit with the cow.
Like the whole idea that you consider it a dangling limb food
while the animal's still alive is bizarre. Maybe we just consider it
to be connected to the cow and one with the cow. Why
do you need this fancy explanation? And I'll show you we say
that in another case, דתניא we taught in a ברייתא: braisa. ייחור
של תאנה, yichur shel te'enah, a limb of an animal now, but
of a tree, of a fig tree, שניפשח she-nifshach that was cracked
off or torn off, ומעורה בקליפתה u-me'ura b'klipatah is still intertwined in
its bark. So it's still sort of dangling limb now from the
tree. Okay, but it's snapped but it's still physically connected. רבי יהודה
מטהר, Rabbi Yehuda metaher, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the fruit on
that is טהור, tahor. it's still considered connected. וחכמים אומרים va-Chachamim omrim
אם יכול לחיות im yachol lichyot טהור, tahor if the limb can
survive, it can you know, reconnect to the tree, then טהור tahor
the fruit is considered connected. ואם לאו ve-im lav and if not,
טמא. Then it's טמא, then it's considered disconnected. ואמרינן לך ve-amrinan lach
and we actually said to you, מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? mai taama
d'Rabbi Yehuda? What is the reason of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
says that the fruit is still considered connected part of the tree,
even though the limb is broken off? ואמרת לן ve-amarta lan and
you said to us, הואיל ומעורה מעורה ho'il u-me'ura me'ura since it's
all intertwined, it's still considered connected. It might not be living from
the tree, but if there's still a physical connection, it's still considered
one. So if you say that about a limb of a tree,
if you're asking what's the reason רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say
a dangling limb from a live animal would not be טמא, say
the simple explanation. Say what you said about the tree. Say if
it's physically connected, even if it's dangling and it's not going to
be, you know, live from the animal anymore, it's still considered part
of the animal. So who needs your fancy explanation? Now what we're
going to see is that this was the explanation that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan offered for רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon Okay, so what we're
going to אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Rabbi Yochanan, So
what we're trying to do here is trying to sort of find
what was the original place where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan offered this
as the explanation of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon Okay, and part of
that is the original question that we asked about when רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says it's טהור, tahor which part of the משנה Mishna.
is he referring to? So we're assuming that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon logic was, it's not כשר kosher to
be eaten, and therefore it's not food. But now we're saying that
can't be the explanation of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon going on the
beginning of the משנה, Mishna because there's a much simpler explanation to
argue on the beginning of the משנה. mishna So this indicates that
רבי שמעון's Rebbe Shimon. statement that it's טהור tahor. is going on
a different case, if it needs this more complicated explanation. So let's
take a look. גמרא Gemara says, so אמר ליה, so he said,
you know what, you're right. אמציעתא. a-mitziata. So רבי שמעון's Rebbe Shimon
statement that it's טהור tahor? is not going on the beginning of
the משנה, mishna that's an easy explanation, it's all physically connected. He's
going on the middle case of the משנה. mishna? What was the
middle case? Remember there's three cases: the animal's alive, the animal's shechted,
the animal died naturally. So the middle case is the animal was
shechted. נשחטה הבהמה, nishchata ha-behemah, the animal is shechted, הוכשרה בדמיה huchshara
b'dameha דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So the blood makes the
limb considered susceptible even though it was dangling. רבי שמעון אומר לא
הוכשרה, Rabbi Shimon omer lo huchshara, the blood did not make the
limb susceptible. Okay, remember that? We had a whole five different explanations
what that debate was about, whether it makes the limb susceptible or
not. So for this, we're going to argue that רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon is, you know, here we're going to apply רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon when he says טהור. tahor, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon at the
end of the משנה mishna, that is טהור, tahor. we're sort of
connecting to this רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon who very explicitly said not
really טהור, tahor, but it's not הוכשר. huchshar. So on that, אמר
רבי יוחנן, מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Amar Rabbi Yochanan, mai ta'ama d'Rebbe
Shimon? What's the reason in the middle that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
said that the blood of the שחיטה shechita does not make this
limb טהור? אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse said: מכל האוכל אשר
יאכל, mikol ha'ochel asher yei'achel. all food that will be eaten. אוכל
שאתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים קרוי אוכל, ochel she'atah yachol le'ahachilo l'acheirim karui
ochel. only if it can be fed to others, אוכל שאי אתה
יכול להאכילו לאחרים אינו קרוי אוכל, ochel she-ei ata yachol le'achilo l'acherim
eino karui ochel, if it can't be fed to others, it's not
food. And therefore when the animal was shechted, the limb isn't הוכשר
huchshar because it's not food. Now that is a really problematic explanation
for two reasons. Number one is then why say the limb isn't
הוכשר? huchshar? It's not about it's not being הוכשר, huchshar, it's about
it being completely excluded from the category of food and it's not
able to become טמא. The other reason that's difficult is why can't
you feed this limb to other people? What can't you feed to
non-Jews? אבר מן החי, בשר מן החי. basar min hachai This was
a dangling limb that you shechted. That's not אבר מן החי. It's
not מותר mutar for Jews to read it, eat it, we learn
from a verse of ובשר בשדה טרפה, u-vasar ba-sadeh tereifa, but it's
not אבר מן החי. So that is a really problematic explanation. Number
one, it's not about being הוכשר, huchshar, it's arguing that it's completely
excluded. And number two is it's not even clear why it can't
be eaten by non-Jews. Anyway, let's see what the answer is. The
גמרא's Gemara going to reject it. So the גמרא says, presumably although
רש"י says that at this stage it's obviously the גמרא's assuming it
can't, but that's surprising. So now anyway the גמרא says, how do
you know that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying? ודילמא טעמא
דרבי שמעון בהאי איכא כדרבי איכא דרבי יוחנן. ve-dilma taama d'Rabbi Shimon
be-hai ika k'Rabbi ika d'Rabbi Yochanan. We had like a whole list
of five different explanations for why that meat does not become הוכשר.
huchshar. Why are you jumping all of a sudden to this new
explanation because it's not considered food? It's not about being considered food,
there's a lot of explanations whether the שחיטה shechita, makes it considered
הוכשר huchshar or not. So that can't be where רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is explaining רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon, So the גמרא says, אלא
לעולם הסיפא והכי. ela le'olam ha'seifa v'hachi. Let's go back to the
simple reading of the משנה mishna, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, is
going on the last case. The dangling limb, the animal died, and
the משנה mishna. says it's a source of טומאה. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon, says it's טהור. Now how could רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say
it's טהור on the last case of the משנה? mishna, When the
animal died, it's either אבר מן החי or אבר מן הנבילה. ever
min haneveilah. So let's see what the גמרא says. So, אלא לעולם
הסיפא, ela le'olam ha'seifa, the last case. לאו אאבר אלא אבשר. lav
a'ever, ela a'basar. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon obviously can't be arguing on
the whole limb, that has to be problematic. But what he's arguing
on is if some of the meat, dangling meat, when the animal
died. So let's take a look. מתה הבהמה הבשר צריך הכשר. meisa
habeheimah, habasar tzarich hechshar. Because if the animal died, the meat is,
okay. So what is the basic story? Right? We say dangling limb,
the animal died, it's like it fell off. So if it is
a whole limb, it falls off, it's אבר מן החי, it causes
טומאה. Let's say it's dangling meat. Dangling meat does not cause טומאה.
So what would it, what's the status of the dangling meat if
the animal died? It would be considered food and it could become
טמא if it had הכשר. That point of the משנה, Mishnah not
about the limb, but about the meat. Isn't that בשר מן החי
basar min hachai, because it hasn't, it is בשר מן החי, basar
min hachai but בשר מן החי basar min hachai. is not a
source of טומאה. Okay. So the last point of the משנה, if
it was dangling meat and the animal died, it's not a source
of טומאה, it's בשר מן החי. basar min hachai, The way it
becomes טמא is if it is, it requires הכשר. On that point
about the dangling meat, non-Jews cannot eat it. Nobody can eat it.
All the prohibitions apply. It's just not a source of טומאה. So
that's the point that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was going on. How
can you say that בשר מן החי, basar min hachai. dangling meat
when the animal died, can become טמא if it has contact with
liquid, since nobody can eat this piece of meat, it can't become
טמא. Okay, that's a nice read of the משנה. So it says,
אלא אבשר מתה. ela a'basar meisa. אלא אבשר. ela a'basar. מתה הבהמה
הבשר צריך הכשר. meisa habeheimah, habasar tzarich hechshar. The animal died, you
had this dangling meat, it's בשר מן החי. basar min hachai, It's
not a source of טומאה, but it will become טמא if it
had הכשר. ורבי שמעון מטהר. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no,
I don't care if it comes in contact with liquid, this meat
will never become טמא. אמר רבי יוחנן מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? אמר
קרא, מכל האוכל אשר יאכל. אוכל שאתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים קרוי אוכל.
אוכל שאי אתה יכול להאכילו לאחרים אין קרוי אוכל. ochel she'ee atah
yachol le'ahachilo l'acheirim ein karui ochel. If you can't eat it and
others can't eat it, it's not food. So בשר מן החי, basar
min hachai and here's your question, Charlie, אבר מן החי is a
source of טומאה. בשר מן החי basar min hachai cannot be considered
food because nobody can eat it and therefore it cannot become טמא.
What do the חכמים Chachamim say? They say the definition of food
goes by its physical ability to be eaten, not by its halachic
ability to be eaten. Okay, that was the end of that. Now
the end of the משנה, as if to say certainly one of
the more memorable earlier משניות had to do with human skin and
human meat. So of course if we've been talking about dangling limbs
of בהמה, beheima, we will end the פרק with dangling limbs of
humans. So let's take a look. האבר והבשר המדולדלים באדם טהורים. ha'ever
v'habasar hameduldalim b'adam tehorim. You gotta be happy that this פרק is
ending in ten minutes. Okay. So הבשר האבר והבשר המדולדלים באדם טהורים.
habasar ha'ever v'habasar hameduldalim b'adam tehorim. You have again a dangling limb
or dangling meat of a human. Right, this actually occurred in real
cases of leprosy. I mean not in what we call, not in
צרעת, but in medical leprosy. I mean limbs would fall off, no?
Yes? Okay, anyway. Okay, you have dangling meat, dangling limb. So it
doesn't have to just be leprosy, it could be other conditions where
a limb could be dangling. Oh really? Well obviously if physical trauma.
Physical trauma. Yeah. Okay. Right, so if it's in a human, טהורים.
tehorim. Okay, they're טהור because they're not אבר מן החי, and we're
certainly not going to suggest like the dangling limb of an animal
that it's considered food. So by a human it has no status.
Right? מת אדם, meis adam, now if the person dies, okay, so
what's, his whole corpse is a source of טומאה, an אבי אבות
הטומאה. avi avot hatumah. הבשר טהור, habasar tahor, the meat, the dangling
meat is טהור because again the idea is that when the death
is natural or whatever, when it's not שחיטה, which is irrelevant to
humans, it's like this thing fell off while he was dying, before
he died. So if a piece of meat fell off from a
human, it's, it's, it's not בשר מן החי basar min hachai, of
a human being is not a source of טומאה. But if a
limb fell off of a human being during his life, אבר מן
החי of a human being is a source of טומאה. So this
person died with a dangling limb, it's like the limb or the
meat fell off. The meat is בשר מן החי, not a source
of טומאה. The dangling limb, like by animals, אבר מן החי is
a source of טומאה. What if the meat is attached to the
limb? No, if it's not, you just have some, some flesh hanging
off. Okay. הבשר טהור האבר מטמא משום אבר מן החי ואינו מטמא
משום אבר מן המת. habasar tahor, ha'ever metamei mishum ever min hachai,
v'eino metamei mishum ever min hameis. It's like it fell off during
life, so it's אבר מן החי, it is not an, it is
not a limb of a corpse. What is the difference? Because as
a, if it were considered part of the corpse, you wouldn't need
the whole limb. Right, a corpse, what parts of a corpse cause
טומאה? Even just a כזית of meat, even a little bit of,
even a little bit of bone, right? But if we considered that
it fell off during life, then its source of טומאה is only
as a איבר, eiver, as a whole limb, and therefore pieces of
it would not be a source of טומאה. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei
Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, and again רבי
שמעון מטהר. Rabbi Shimon metaher. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's טהור.
Now we're going to have a much harder time with this רבי
שמעון, because the other one we could say it had to do
with whether it's considered food or not. It has nothing to be
considered food, so what is he doing saying that this limb, dangling
limb of this human is completely טהור? We will see in the
גמרא. Yeah, very good. You know what? I'm going to have to
hold off the questions. We have six minutes. No, I gotta—I just
said I'm holding off the questions. Let's read the גמרא. רבי שמעון,
ממה נפשך. manafshach. רבי שמעון, make up your mind. אם מיתה עושה
ניפול, Im misah osa nipol, if it's like the limb fell off
when you were dying, when the person was dying, let it be
טמא משום איבר מן החי. mishum eiver min hachai. And if—we're assuming
איבר מן החי eiver min hachai is a source of טומאה by
humans. You're right, we haven't demonstrated it, we're assuming it. ואם מיתה
עושה ניפול, Ve'im misah osa nipol, and if like when the person
died, it's—the limb did not fall off, let it be טמא משום
איבר מן המת. mishum eiver min hamais. So then it's part of
a corpse, and of course it's a source of טומאה. So the
גמרא says, רבי שמעון בעלמא קאי. Rabbi Shimon be'alma kai. רבי שמעון
is talking generally, not specifically this case. דקאמר תנא קמא, De'ka'amar tanna
kamma, the author of the משנה said, האיבר מטמא משום איבר מן
החי ואינו מטמא משום איבר מן המת. ha'eiver metamei mishum eiver min
hachai ve'aino metamei mishum eiver min hamais. That the limb is a
source of טומאה as an איבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, not
as a limb from a corpse. אלמא, Alma, from the תנא קמא's
tanna kamma statement it's implicit, איבר מן המת בעלמא מטמא. eiver min
hamais be'alma metamei. A limb of a corpse normally is a source
of טומאה. דאמר ליה רבי שמעון, De'amar lei Rabbi Shimon, and to
this רבי שמעון is responding, when he says it's טהור, I don't
mean an איבר מן החי eiver min hachai is טהור. איבר מן
החי Eiver min hachai I agree with you is טמא. But what
I'm saying is, איבר מן המת בעלמא לא מטמא, eiver min hamais
be'alma lo metamei, that an איבר מן המת eiver min hamais is
not טמא, which is bizarre. I mean, it's from a whole מת
mais which is a source of טומאה. איבר המת. Eiver hamais. Thank
you. The point is like this: assuming you have a very small
limb that does not have enough of the other—of any of the
components. There's not enough meat to cause טומאה. Now obviously a tiny
little bone causes טומאה. So, but there was an opinion before that
to be an איבר eiver you didn't need a bone. Or maybe
we're talking about טומאת אוהל. tumat ohel. So a piece of bone
doesn't cause טומאת אוהל. tumat ohel. So it's a small little limb
which does not have the ability to cause טומאה based on its
meat alone or based on its limb alone, or based on the
bone, and you want it to cause טומאה as its identity as
a limb. That's the case of איבר מן המת. eiver min hamais.
Certainly meat from the מת, Mais, if you have enough, causes טומאה.
Bone of a מת causes טומאה by touch. But is an איבר,
eiver, an entire small little small little limb, I don't know, a
pinky or whatever it might be—that has bone. Okay, so that's bone.
So let's say we're talking about אוהל. ohel. Or we're talking about
something that if you assume you don't need bone, like like lips,
okay, or an organ, if it's not enough meat, does—is that identity
as a limb enough to make it considered a source of טומאה
from a corpse? So there רבי שמעון says a bizarre thing. Well,
if it came off from a live human, then its identity of
a limb is a source of טומאה. If it came off from
a corpse and you didn't have enough of the other stuff there,
its identity as a limb is not a source of טומאה. That's
what we're saying רבי שמעון is saying. And now we're going to
see how the גמרא sort of is astounded about this, or whatever,
quotes a ברייתא that's astounded. Okay, so it says like this: דתניא,
where are we? We taught in a ברייתא. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar
Rabbi Eliezer, so now we're aligning רבי שמעון with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. Said רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, שמעתי שאיבר מן החי מטמא. shamati
she'eiver min hachai metamei. I heard that a limb from a live
person causes טומאה. And it's implicit from the response that he means
only a limb from a live person, a limb from a dead—from
a corpse, if there wasn't enough flesh, would not cause טומאה. So
אמר לו רבי יהושע, amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua, so רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua said to him, מן החי ולא מן המת? min hachai velo
min hamais? Only a limb from a live person, not a limb
from a dead person? וקל וחומר, Vekal vachomer, you should make a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה חי שהוא טהור, Ma chai shehu tahor,
a live person fundamentally he's טהור, איבר הפורש ממנו טמא, eiver haporesh
mimenu tamei, and nevertheless if a limb falls from a live person,
it becomes a source of טומאה. מת, a corpse, שהוא טמא, shehu
tamei, the whole corpse is טמא, לא כל שכן, lo kol sheken,
how much more so should a limb from a corpse, even if
there isn't enough flesh on it, be considered a source of טומאה.
And I'll give you—I'll give you a proof about how you have
to think, you know, about this type of logic, the absurdity of
your logic. כתוב במגילת תענית, Kasuv beMegillas Taanis, it says in מגילת
תענית, Megillas Taanis, which is where was that coming from? It was
a list of written up of days, little minor holidays you don't
fast on. So one of the things it says in מגילת תענית
Megillas Taanis is, פסחא זעירא, Pischa Zeira, the small פסח, Pesach, פסח
שני Pesach Sheni in אייר, Iyar, דלא למספד, delo lemispad, you don't
eulogize on פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So if I were you, said
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, should I read
it to say, הרבא למספד? ha'rabba lemispad? So the פסח ראשון Pesach
Rishon you can do a הספד hesped on? So okay, you heard
a tradition that says איבר מן החי eiver min hachai is מטמא.
metamei. It doesn't mean איבר מן המת eiver min hamais is not
מטמא. metamei. It means even איבר מן החי eiver min hachai is
מטמא. So, so, so he said back, אלא כל שכן, ela kol
sheken, he called—of course it's a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, פסח ראשון.
Pesach Rishon. הכא נמי כל שכן, Hacha nami kol sheken, here too,
if an איבר מן החי eiver min hachai causes טומאה, an איבר
מן המת eiver min hamais causes טומאה. So אמר ליה, he said
back to him, כך שמעתי, kach shamati, what do you want from
me? This is how I heard the tradition: only איבר מן החי,
eiver min hachai, not איבר מן המת. eiver min hamais. So when
רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* in our משנה *mishna* is saying it's טהור
*tahor*, he means איבר מן המת *eiver min hameis* is טהור *tahor*,
assuming again there's not sufficient flesh. Okay, now we're moving on, wrapping
up the משנה *mishna*. Just stick with me, I know it's already
8:30, but I want to get to the end here. ומה איכא
בין איבר מן החי לאיבר מן המת *umai ika bein eiver min
hachai le'eiver min hameis*? When the משנה *mishna* says that this limb
that's like it fell off is like an איבר מן החי *eiver
min hachai* and not an איבר מן המת *eiver min hameis*, what
difference does it make? Either way it's a source of טומאה *tumah*
at the end of the משנה *mishna*, assuming both are considered טמא
*tamei*. So here's the difference: כזית בשר ועצם כשעורה הפורש מאיבר מן
החי איכא בינייהו *kezayis basar ve'etzem kesiora haporesh me'eiver min hachai ika
beinaihu*. But by an איבר מן החי *eiver min hachai*, like we
said before, you need the whole limb. If a piece of meat
came off of the limb, or a piece of bone, if it
was an איבר מן החי *eiver min hachai*, that's not a source
of טומאה *tumah*. The only thing that's a source of טומאה *tumah*
is the entire limb. But if it's considered part of the corpse,
then even if you just had a certain amount of flesh or
a certain amount of bone without the whole limb, it would also
continue to be a source of טומאה *tumah*. דתנן *detnan*, we taught
in a משנה *mishna*: כזית בשר הפורש מאיבר מן החי *kezayis basar
haporesh me'eiver min hachai*, רבי אליעזר מטמא *Rebbi Eliezer metamei*, רבי אליעזר
*Rebbi Eliezer* says it's טמא *tamei*. That's interesting, so even though by
a בהמה *beheima* בשר מן החי *basar min hachai* is not a
problem, here he says by a human בשר מן החי *basar min
hachai* is טמא *tamei*. ורבי נחוניא בן הקנה ורבי יהושע מטהרין *veReb
Nechunya ben HaKana veRebbi Yehoshua metaherin*, and רבי נחוניא בן הקנה *Reb
Nechunya ben HaKana* and רבי יהושע *Rebbi Yehoshua* say no, no, בשר
מן החי *basar min hachai* by a human is not an issue.
עצם כשעורה הפורש מאיבר מן החי *etzem kesiora haporesh me'eiver min hachai*,
let's say it's a little piece of bone. So here the sides
change. רבי נחוניא מטמא *Reb Nechunya metamei*, here רבי נחוניא *Reb Nechunya*
says that that is טמא *tamei* by an איבר מן החי *eiver
min hachai* of a human. So again, איבר מן החי *eiver min
hachai* of a human according to some opinions is more strict than
of a בהמה *beheima*. בהמה *beheima*, you need the whole איבר *eiver*.
Here there are some opinions that say even some of the flesh
of it, even some of the bone of it, without being a
whole איבר *eiver*, is enough. But רבי יהושע *Rebbi Yehoshua* consistently says,
רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע מטהרין *Rebbi Eliezer veRebbi Yehoshua metaherin*, that no,
you need the whole limb by a human like the whole limb
of a בהמה *beheima*, and any piece of it is not a
source of טומאה *tumah*. So that way איבר מן המת *eiver min
hameis* is stricter. איבר מן המת *eiver min hameis* as a corpse,
flesh is enough, bone is enough. By איבר מן החי *eiver min
hachai*, you need the whole thing, and even there are some opinions
here that maybe flesh or bone as well, but certainly not all
of those would be a source of טומאה *tumah*, whereas by a
מת *meis*, even flesh by itself, even bone by itself. And now
the גמרא *Gemara* just wraps up: השתא דאתית להכי *hasha de'asis le'hachi*,
now that we've come to that point that there's debates about how
much of an איבר מן החי *eiver min hachai* causes טומאה *tumah*,
בין תנא קמא ורבי שמעון נמי כזית בשר ועצם כשעורה איכא בינייהו
*bein tana kama veRebbi Shimon nami kezayis basar ve'etzem kesiora ika beinaihu*.
When רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* says it's טהור *tahor*, we don't have
to have him saying the extreme position that איבר מן המת *eiver
min hameis* is טהור *tahor*. Maybe when he's saying טהור *tahor*, he's
arguing about pieces that come off from an איבר מן החי *eiver
min hachai*. So the תנא קמא *tana kama* would say some pieces
that come off from an איבר מן החי *eiver min hachai* are
טמא *tamei*, maybe the meat is טמא *tamei*, maybe the bone is
טמא *tamei*, you don't need the whole איבר *eiver*, and רבי שמעון
*Rebbi Shimon* is saying no, no, no, only the whole איבר *eiver*
of an איבר מן החי *eiver min hachai* is טמא *tamei*, any
piece that comes off from it would be טהור *tahor*. But certainly
the last line of רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* saying טהור *tahor* is
hard to read him across the board, so we have him in
more limited cases, either איבר מן המת *eiver min hameis* is טהור
*tahor* if there's not enough flesh, or when something separates from an
איבר מן החי *eiver min hachai*, that is טהור *tahor*. הדרן עלך
העור והרוטב *Hadarun lach or veharotev*.